Guide to the Suzanne Harris Papers MSS.547
Fales Library and Special Collections
Suzanne Harris Papers
1960-2014
1970-1979
Fales Library and Special Collections
Harris, Suzanne
Hydler, Glenda
MSS.547
11.84 Linear Feet in 9 manuscript boxes, 1 record carton, 1 half manuscript box, 2 flat boxes, 2 oversized flat boxes, 8 flat-file-folders, 15 folders in shared oversized boxes, 2 vinyl records in a shared LP box, 11 folders in a shared flat boxes, and 6 audiocassette tapes in a shared cassette box.
2 Digital_Betacam
8 sound tape reels
12 Half_Inch_Video_Reel
7 audiocassettes
2 Sound_Disc--Vinyl
3 film reels
3.42 Gigabytes in 15 digital files
Suzanne Harris (1940-1979) was a New York City-based artist whose work has been exhibited domestically and internationally. She was a member of SoHo's 112 Greene Street artistic community in the early 1970s. The Suzanne Harris Papers (1960-2014) consists of materials created and collected by artist Suzanne Harris and documents her artistic processes and output. Materials in this collection include photographic documentation of her exhibitions including negatives, slides, and prints; press clippings and reviews of exhibitions in various publications; lecture notes and course syllabi; proposals for projects including artist statements, project summaries, and proposed budgets; exhibition ephemera and administrative papers; documents relating to the posthumous sale and use of Harris' works; as well as recordings of her performances and projects. The collection also includes original drawings and some objects related to Harris' personal life.
Arrangement
Materials in the collection have been arranged alphabetically by topic. Art exhibitions and installations have been grouped by gallery.
Scope and Contents
The Suzanne Harris Papers (1960-2014) is composed of paper and audiovisual materials documenting Harris' life and work as an artist and arts educator. The collection contains materials created and collected by Harris and documents her artistic processes and output, as well as her installations and exhibitions held in the United States, mainly in New York City, as well as abroad in locations including France, Germany, and Italy.
Materials in this collection include photographic documentation of her exhibitions including negatives, slides, and prints; press clippings and reviews of exhibitions in various publications; lecture notes and course syllabi; proposals for projects including artist statements, project summaries, and proposed budgets; original art, paintings, drawings, and sketches; original writings; exhibition ephemera and administrative papers; documents relating to the posthumous sale and use of Harris' works; as well as recordings of her performances and projects. Together, these materials highlight the types of exhibitions Harris created and participated in, her various inspirations for art pieces, the types of classes she was teaching, and the ways in which she was perceived by her colleagues and critics. Personal photographs of Suzanne Harris, her friends, and colleagues also provide insight about her private life.
The Suzanne Harris Papers contain materials related to sculptor Jene Highstein and art curator Glenda Hydler -- both of whom were Harris' colleagues and close friends. Monographs focused upon Highstein's work and career, as well as some reviews of his works are included in the collections. Glenda Hydler's posters, which she made for Harris, and personal notes that mainly address Harris' death are also included. The collection contains correspondence between Harris and Hydler that address both personal and business affairs, as well as personal photographs of Harris, Highstein, and Hydler. Between 1974 and 1975, Harris and Hydler recorded conversations addressing topics such as secrets and interpersonal relationships. Those conversations can be found in the collection. Throughout the 1970s, Harris recorded videos, some of which featured Highstein and Harris. Audiovisual projects found within the collection have been listed with the original titles found on their containers.
The collection also contains some materials related to Harris' ex-husband, Paul Harris, including descriptions of their horoscopes and photographs of the couple. Paul Harris was a musician and worked as a keyboard player. He was featured on two studio albums, Down the Road by Manhassas and the Souther-Hillman-Furay Band's self-titled album. Copies of both vinyl records can be found within this collection.
Finally, the Suzanne Harris Papers contain various objects belonging to Harris including glass jars, a silver spoon, bells, a glass ash tray, a tambourine, remnants of a drum, pencil cases, and some pieces of clothing. The origins of these items is unknown.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Glenda Hydler in July 2018; the accession number with this gift is 2018.101.
Biographical Note
Suzanne Harris (1940-1979) was a New York City-based artist whose work has been exhibited domestically and internationally. Before becoming an artist, Harris studied medicine. In the early 1970s, she moved to New York City and became a member of SoHo's 112 Greene Street experimental artistic community. 112 Greene Street was an exhibition and performance space located inside an abandoned SoHo factory. All artists were welcome to use the space as long as they were willing to install and dismantle their own work. Throughout the 1970s, Suzanne Harris exhibited several performances, such as Flying Machines, and art pieces, such as Steel Pipes, at 112 Greene Street. As an artist, Harris was interested in the movement of the human body and explored this through dance. She performed alongside dancers Steve Paxton, Trisha Brown, and others. She was also interested in sculpture and created art installations including Locus Up One, The Tower of Power, and Sunstroak. In addition to being a working artist, Suzanne Harris was also an arts educator and taught a Sensory Awareness course at the Pratt Institute in New York City.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Access to some audiovisual materials in this collection is available through digitized access copies. Researchers may view an item's original container, but the media themselves are not available for playback because of preservation concerns. Materials that have already been digitized are noted in the collection's finding aid and can be requested in our reading room.
Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact [Fales Library, special.collections@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596] with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Born-Digital Access Policies and Procedures
An access terminal for born-digital materials in the collection is available by appointment for reading room viewing and listening only. Researchers may view an item's original container and/or carrier, but the physical carriers themselves are not available for use because of preservation concerns.
Art, Modern -- United States -- 20th century -- Exhibitions; Drawings (visual works); Artists -- United States -- 20th century; Photographs.; Artifacts.; Press releases.; Negatives (photographic); Sketchbooks.; Drawings; Posters.; Audiovisual materials.; Lecture notes.; Syllabi.; New York (N.Y.).; Hydler, Glenda; Harris, Suzanne; Highstein, Jene, 1942-2013; 112 Greene Street (Gallery)
- 112 Greene St. (New York City) -- Exhibition Materials (Templates), circa 1970s (Box 1, Folder 1, Box Shared Fales 043, Folder 11)
- 112 Greene St. (New York City) -- Flying Machine, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 2, Box 8, Folder 1)
- 112 Greene St. (New York City) -- MEM, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 3, Box 8, Folder 2)
- 112 Greene St. (New York City) -- One/Four, 1973-1976 (Box 8, Folder 3)
- 112 Greene St. (New York City) -- The Return of the Square, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 4, Box 8)
- 112 Greene St. (New York City) -- Steel Pipes, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 5, Box 8)
- 112 Greene St. (New York City) -- Suzanne Harris' Personal Photographs & Negatives, 1970-1972 (Box 1, Folder 6, Box Shared Fales 096, Folder 1)
- 112 Greene St. (New York City) -- Untitled Cardboard Installation, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- 112 Greene St. (New York City) -- Wheels, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 8, Box 8, Folder 6)
- 112 Greene St. (New York City) -- Won for the One, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- 112 Greene St. (New York City) -- Z, circa 1970s (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Address Book, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Administrative Papers -- General, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Administrative Papers -- Reproduction Requests, 1981, 1994, 1999, 2007-2008 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Alternatives in Retrospect: An Historical Overview, 1969-1975, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- American Cultural Center Exhibition (Paris, France), 1975 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Art Park (Lewistown, NY) -- Correspondence, 1978-1979 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Art Park (Lewistown, NY) -- Haniel the Light Splitter, 1978 (Box 8, Folder 7)
- Art Park (Lewistown, NY) -- The Light Splitter, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Art Park (Lewistown, NY) -- Sunstroak, 1974; cuid40932 (Box 2, Folder 3, Box 8, Folder 8, Box Shared Fales 099, 16mm film reels 547.0034)
- Artist Statements - Suzanne Harris Explaining Her Art, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- "Bag Lady - Suzanne Harris (Video tape Juan Downey)", undated; cuid41181 (Box 15, Half inch video reel 547.0018)
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
  Duration: 4 minutes; Preservation note: Transferred twice using different signal paths to stabilize video. Both takes retained. Poor quality with damage throughout, required baking twice.
- "Batman - Propoganda for American Avoidance Syndrome" by Suzanne Harris, 1977 (Box Shared Fales 093, Folder 4-6)
- Ben Shahn Galleries (New Jersey) -- Exhibition Programs, circa 1970s (Box 2, Folder 5)
- "Birds at Woodstock", undated; cuid40958 (Box Shared Fales 094, Audiocassette 547.0024)
- Brooklyn Studio, circa 1974, 1977 (Box 8, Folder 9)
- California Institute of Arts (CalArts), 1979 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- "City Hall - pillars, shoe repair shop, 14th st subway, dance segment, suzie working on outdoor piece", 1975; cuid41185 (Box 15, Half inch video reel 547.0022)
  Duration: 33 minutes; Preservation note: Noticable line of tape damage in sections.
- "Clocktower" by Robert Petersen Poster, 1979 (Box Shared Fales 093, Folder 8)
- Collage of Suzanne Harris' International Travels, undated (Flat-file-folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Correspondence - David Findlay, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Correspondence - Keith Sonnier, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- "Dissolve (#2)", undated; cuid41177 (Box 15, Half inch video reel 547.0011)
  Scope and Contents
  Content warning: This recording contains nudity.
  Duration: 29 minutes
- Drawings of Wheels, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Documentation of All Drawings and Objects (Photographs and Negatives), circa 1970s (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Domestic Travels (Negatives), circa 1970s (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Down the Road by Manassas, 1973 (Box Shared Fales 046, Sound disc--vinyl 547.003)
- Early Photographs of Suzanne Harris, circa 1960s-1970s (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Egg Sculpture, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
- European Installations, 1977-1978 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Exhibition Promotional Materials, 1975-1980, 1989, 2012 (Box 2, Folder 16, Box Shared Fales 093, Folder 10, Box Shared Fales 096, Folder 2)
- France (Paris) -- 10th Bienneale de Paris, 1977 (Box 8, Folder 10)
- France (Paris) -- Focus, 1978 (Box 8, Folder 11)
- Franklin Furnace Archive, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Franklin Furnace Posthumous Suzanne Harris Exhibition, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Franklin Furance -- Tape of Suzanne Harris Reading, 1978; cuid41269 (Box 10, Quarter inch audio reel 547.0003, Box 7, Folder 12)
  Duration: 41 minutes; Preservation Note: No content in the left channel. Right channel contains sound effects and bits of music with from one to three minutes of silence between each section.
- Galerie Ala (Milan, Italy) -- Dalet Series, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Galerie December (Dusseldorf, Germany), 1977 (Box 3, Folder 4, Box 8, Folder 12)
- Galerie Mollet-Vieville (Paris, France), 1977 (Box 3, Folder Unknown, Box 8, Folder 13)
- Glenda Hydler (Curator), 1979 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Glenda Hydler -- Art for Suzanne Harris, 1977 (Box Shared Fales 096, Folder 3)
- Glenda Hydler -- Photographs of Suzanne Harris, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Glenda Hydler -- Posters for Suzanne Harris, 1979 (Box Shared Fales 086, Folder 20)
- Hal Bromm Gallery (New York City) -- Introductory Show, 1977 (Box 8, Folder 14)
- Hal Bromm Gallery (New York City) -- Rectangular Oval, 1978 (Box 8, Folder 15)
- Hal Bromm Gallery (New York City) -- Stucco Works, 1975, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Hal Bromm Gallery (New York City) -- Untitled Glass Piece, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- "Hands", 1974; cuid41183 (Box 15, Half inch video reel 547.0020)
  Duration: 19 minutes
- Holly Solomon Gallery (New York City) -- Dalet Series, 1977 (Box 8, Folder 16, Box Shared Fales 096, Folder 4)
- Holly Solomon Gallery: The First Two Years, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Holly Solomon Gallery -- Locus Up One, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 10-13, Box 4, Folder 1, Box 8, Folder 17, Flat-file-folder 1 Right)
- Holly Solomon Gallery -- Locus Up One, 1976 (Box Shared Fales 086, Folder 21-22, Box Shared Fales 093, Folder 11, Box Shared Fales 096, Folder 5)
- Holly Solomon Gallery -- Untitled Piece, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- The Hudson River Museum (Yonkers, NY) -- Baby Jane, 1973, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 3, Box 8, Folder 18)
- International Travels -- China, 1978-1979 (Box 4, Folder 4-5)
- International Travels -- Various (Greece, Egypt, Haiti, St. Lucia, India), circa 1960s-1970s (Box 4, Folder 6)
- James Yu Gallery (New York City) -- Stucco Works, 1975, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Jeff Lew (Sculptor) - Hartford Art School, 1971
  - Mixed Materials (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Video, cuid41188 (Box 15, Half inch video reel 547.0006)
    Duration: 8 minutes; Preservation note: Tape in poor condition, poorly shot, and there are tape speed issues towards end of tape.
- Jene Highstein (Sculptor), 1979-1980 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Jene Highstein Family -- Collage, undated (Box Shared Fales 043, Folder 13)
- Jene Highstein: Five Black Cement Sculptures, 1977 (Box Shared Fales 096, Folder 6)
- Jene Highstein and Suzanne Harris at Harris' Cabin (Woodstock, NY), circa 1970s (Box 4, Folder 8)
- "Jene and Suzie talking about cats and dogs and territory", undated; cuid41178 (Box 15, Half inch video reel 547.0014)
  Duration: 11 minutes
- Lance Fung Gallery (New York City) -- Consignment Information for Harris' Works, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Lance Fung Gallery (New York City) -- Won for One, 1974, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 10, Box 8, Folder 19)
- MoMA PS 1 -- After the Math, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 11, Box 9, Folder 1, Box Shared Fales 043, Folder 12, Box Shared Fales 093, Folder 7)
- MoMA PS 1 -- Newspaper Scenes for Information Exhibition, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 12)
- MoMA PS 1 -- Peace for the Temporal Highway (Part of the Rooms series), 1976 (Box 4, Folder 13)
- MoMA PS 1 -- Tower of Power, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 14, Box 9, Folder 2, Flat-file-folder 3, Box Shared Fales 096, Folder 11)
- More I Remember by Joe Brainard, 1972 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- New Hampshire Academie of Dance (NHAD) Performances and Rehearsals, 1971-1974
  7 minutes
  - Audio (Box 10, Quarter inch audio reel 547.0004)
  - Audio (Box 10, Quarter inch audio reel 547.0005)
  - Audio, cuid41089 (Box 15, Quarter inch audio reel 547.0008)
    Duration: 68 minutes; Preservation note: Consists of four separate recordings of the same piece of music and from the same source, with increasingly long gaps between each recording. These gaps were left intact on the master, but removed from the access copy.
  - Video, cuid41186 (Box 15, Half inch video reel 547.0007)
    Duration: 7 minutes; Preservation note: Vertical sync issues.
- The Norman Fisher Collection at the Jacksonville Art Museum: A Collection, A Collective, 1980 (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Original Art, Paintings, Drawings, and Sketches, undated (Box 5, Folder 5, Flat-file-folder 1 Left, Flat-file-folder 2 Left, Flat-file-folder 4, Flat-file-folder 3)
- Original Art, Paintings, Drawings, and Sketches, undated (Flat-file-folder 5, Box Shared Fales 086, Folder 23, Box Shared Fales 093, Folder 9, Box Shared Fales 096, Folder 7-9)
- Original Art, Paintings, Drawings, and Sketches -- 14 Diazotypes, undated (Flat-file-folder 1 Right)
- Original Art, Paintings, Drawings, and Sketches -- 95 (a-d), undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Original Art, Paintings, Drawings, and Sketches -- 96 (a-d), undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
- Original Art, Paintings, Drawings, and Sketches -- 104 (a-c), undated (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Original Art, Paintings, Drawings, and Sketches -- Contact Sheets and Negatives, 1972-1975 (Box 5, Folder 3-4)
- Original Writings, 1974-1979 (Box 7, Folder 5-8, Box Shared Fales 093, Folder 12)
- Paul Harris, 1968-1970 (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Personal Photographs -- Negatives, undated (Box 5, Folder 10)
- Photographs of Suzanne Harris, undated (Box 5, Folder 11)
- Photographs of Suzanne Harris at Work, circa 1970s (Box 5, Folder 12)
- Posthumous Sale of Suzanne Harris' Works, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 13)
- Pratt Institute -- Teaching Materials for Sensory Awareness Course, 1971-1972 (Box 5, Folder 14)
- Press about Suzanne Harris, 1971-1980 (Box 5, Folder 15, Box Shared Fales 086, Folder 24)
- Proposal -- Gateway National Recreational Area Group Project, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 16)
- Proposal --The Light Machine, 1973 (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Proposal -- Van Cortland Park, 1979 (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Rachel Lew Performance -- Rubber Thoughts on the Way to Florida, 1971 (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Research Materials -- Suntrack Pyramids (Model for Sculpture), 1976-1979 (Box 6, Folder 4, Box Shared Fales 096, Folder 10)
- Robert Stefanotti (Art Dealer), 1979-1980 (Box 6, Folder 5, Flat-file-folder 3)
- Robert Stefanotti -- Appraisal of Harris Estate and Foundations, 1982-1985 (Box 6, Folder 6)
- "S. Harris (#8)", undated (Box 15, Quarter inch audio reel 547.0009)
- Sculpture Center (New York City) -- Decoys, Complexes, and Triggers: Feminism and Land Art in the 1970s, 2008 (Box 6, Folder 7)
- Sketchbooks, undated (Box Shared Fales 086, Folder 25)
- Small Casting, 1978 (Box 6, Folder 8)
- The Souther-Hillman-Furay Band by the Souther-Hillman-Furay Band, 1974 (Box Shared Fales 046, Sound disc--vinyl 547.0031)
- Squared Circle, 1978 (Box 9, Folder 3)
- "St. Mark's", 1976; cuid41180 (Box 15, Half inch video reel 547.0017)
  Duration: 33 minutes
- Stage Design for Mabou Mines, 1979 (Box 6, Folder 9)
- Studying Hungry by Bernadette Mayer, 1975 (Box 6, Folder 10)
- Suzanne Harris Archives Tapes, 2014; cuid40933 (Box 10, Digital betacam 547.0001, 547.0002)
  Duration: 134 minutes in two parts
- Suzanne Harris and Glenda Hydler Discussions, 1974-1975; cuid39078 (Box Shared Fales 094, Audiocassette 547.0023, 547.0025-547.0029, Box Shared Fales 099, 16mm film reels 547.0032, Box 15, Quarter inch audio reel 547.0012, Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_547_ER_1)
- Suzanne Harris Interview with Denise Shavers, undated (Box 6, Folder 11)
- Suzanne Harris Involvement with Music Industry, circa 1960s (Box 6, Folder 12)
- Suzanne Harris Objects and Clothing, circa 1960s-1970s (Box 11, Box 12, Box 13, Box 14)
- Suzanne Harris Passport, undated (Box 6, Folder 13)
- Suzanne Harris Personal Photographs, circa 1960s-1970s (Box 6, Folder 14)
- Suzanne Harris and Psychoanalysis, 1975; cuid39079 (Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_547_ER_2)
- Suzanne Harris Resumes and Curriculum Vitae, circa 1960s-1970s (Box 7, Folder 1)
- Suzanne Harris Slides Information, undated (Box 7, Folder 2)
- "Suzie on camera, Gene/Art Park (#3)", undated; cuid41179 (Box 15, Half inch video reel 547.0015)
  Duration: 21 minutes; Preservation note: Noticable line of tape damage throughout.
- "Suzie/Dance", 1975; cuid41184 (Box 15, Half inch video reel 547.0021)
  Duration: 32 minutes; Preservation note: Noticable line of tape damage throughout.
- "Territory/Hydler", undated
  - Mixed Materials (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Video, cuid41187 (Box 15, Half inch video reel 547.0016)
    Duration: 23 minutes
- "Thunder (#6)", undated (Box 15, Quarter inch audio reel 547.0013)
- Travel Performances, 1964-1976 (Box 9, Folder 4)
- Unfinished "Sefirot" Kabbalah Drawing, undated (Flat-file-folder Shared Special Collections 003)
- "Untitled (#9)", undated (Box 15, Quarter inch audio reel 547.0010)
- Untitled Film, undated; cuid41270 (Box Shared Fales 099, 16mm film reels 547.0033)
- Untitled Installations with Glass, undated, 1976, 1978 (Box 7, Folder 3, Box 9, Folder 5)
- Untitled Pieces, 1976-1977 (Box 9, Folder 6)
- Untitled Photographs and Negatives, undated (Box 7, Folder 4, Box Shared Fales 096, Folder 12)
- Untitled Photographs of Dancers, undated (Box Shared Fales 096, Folder 13)
- "Walking with Camera", undated; cuid41182 (Box 15, Half inch video reel 547.0019)
  Duration: 17 minutes; Preservation note: Noticable line of tape damage throughout, horizontal distortion recorded on tape.
- Whitney Museum at Cherry Street (New York City) -- Inhabitant, 1975 (Box 9, Folder 7)
- Whitney Museum at Cherry Street (New York City) -- Pie, 1975 (Box 7, Folder 9, Box 9, Folder 8)
- Wood Beams -- Germany, France, Italy, Hudson River Museum, 1977-1978 (Box 7, Folder 10)
- Works by Other Artists, undated (Box 7, Folder 11)